{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Prior to coining this three-word phrase, the organization that developed it controversially referred to one of its subjects as a “nincompoop.” An iconic image displaying this phrase shows a man traveling by train from Independence, Missouri to Washington DC. A forecast by Arthur Sears Henning inspired this phrase, a prediction made after polls indicated a Democratic defeat in the 1948 election. For ten points, name this false headline published by the Chicago Daily Tribune.",
      "answer": "Dewey Defeats Truman"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this city has a dream in which he sees a statue with a gold head, a bronze belly, and clay feet. A Biblical figure partially named for this city is described as sitting on top of a scarlet beast with seven heads and ten horns. The Book of Ezekiel was composed while Ezekiel was in this city, which names a whore encountered in the Book of Revelation. The Book of Daniel tells of Nebuchadnezzar II, the ruler of, for ten points, what city where the Jews were held in a namesake period of captivity?",
      "answer": [
        "Babylon",
        "Whore of Babylon",
        "Babylonian Captivity"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern day country obtained de facto independence from the Holy Roman Empire after the Swabian War. France obtained Burgundy shortly after Charles the Bold died fighting a force primarily from this country at the Battle of Nancy. German Landsknechts imitated pike and halberd-wielding mercenaries from this country, whose neutrality was affirmed during the Thirty Years War. For ten points, name this Alpine country with capital at Bern that remained neutral in both world wars.",
      "answer": [
        "Switzerland",
        "Old Swiss Confederacy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer likely hired horn players from Bohemia for the premiere of a piece whose first suite, in F major, includes an “Adagio e staccato” movement. This composer included “La Paix” [la pay] in a suite for wind band written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle, and he included hornpipes in a piece written for a concert for King George I held on a barge on the Thames. For ten points, name this German-born English composer of Music for the Royal Fireworks and Water Music.",
      "answer": "George Friedrich Handel"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician with this surname campaigned with a Frankenstein doll that declared “You have nothing to fear with” that man. A woman with this surname won the Senate seat made available by the retirement of Jesse Helms; that woman with this married surname served as Secretary of Transportation under Ronald Reagan and Secretary of Labor under George W. Bush. For ten points, give this surname shared by North Carolina senator Elizabeth and a Kansas senator who lost the 1996 presidential election to Bill Clinton, Bob.",
      "answer": [
        "Dole",
        "Elizabeth Dole",
        "Bob Dole"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man said “I am very sorry it is taking me so long to die” after attempting suicide during his arrest. The Imperial Rule Assistance Political Association was created by this man, who suggested not executing the pilots of the Doolittle Raid in fear of American retaliation. After being arrested, this man was given a new pair of dentures which had the phrase “remember Pearl Harbor” written in Morse Code. For ten points, name this politician who served as Japan’s Prime Minister from 1941 to 1944.",
      "answer": "Hideki Tojo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker’s concept of the “efficient cause” in the natural world was continued by his successor, Theophrastus. A graded scale of perfection established by this man to classify living organisms is known as his “Great Chain of Being.” This philosopher, who was exiled by Eurymedon the Hierophant, was accused by Hagnothemis of poisoning his most famous pupil, Alexander the Great. For ten points, name this Ancient Greek founder of the Lyceum and student of Plato.",
      "answer": "Aristotle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Andrew Oliver was tasked with implementing this act, after which he was burned in effigy by the Loyal Nine. Thomas Hutchinson’s mansion was ransacked in response to this act. Isaac Barre coined the term “sons of liberty” during a debate over this act, which prompted Samuel Adams to found the Sons of Liberty. When this act was repealed alongside a reduced Sugar Act, Britain also passed the 1766 Declaratory Act. For ten points, name this colonial tax on printed material.",
      "answer": "Stamp Act of 1765"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edouard de Laboulaye proposed this structure as an international effort. After this structure was completed on Bedloe’s Island, it was celebrated with its city’s first ticker-tape parade. This monument’s base features an Emma Lazarus poem with the verses “give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses” called “The New Colossus.” For ten points, name this Frederic Bartholdi-designed sculpture that bears a copper torch in New York Harbor.",
      "answer": [
        "Statue of Liberty or Liberty Enlightening the World",
        "La Libert´e E´clairant le Monde"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader in these conflicts saw a vision of three suns before his victory at Mortimer’s Cross. For switching sides in these conflicts, Richard Neville, the Earl of Warwick, was known as the Kingmaker. These conflicts ended when Richard III was defeated by Henry VII at Bosworth, ushering in the Tudor dynasty. For ten points, name these conflicts between the rival English houses of Lancaster and York, named for their respective red and white flower badges.",
      "answer": "Wars of the Roses"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many perpetrators of this event were tried in Gacaca courts due to a backlog in the traditional justice system. The large number of refugees fleeing this event led to the Great Lakes Crisis in a neighboring country. This event was hastened by rebel forces taking Gisenyi two weeks after the Interahamwe militia lost the capital city of Kigali. Paul Kagame [kuh-GAH-may] became Vice President after the end of, for ten points, what 1994 event in which the Hutus massacred their Tutsi countrymen in a central African country?",
        "answer": [
          "Rwandan Genocide",
          "descriptions of the genocide of the Tutsis/by the Hutus until “Hutu” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Rwandan Genocide, Paul Rusesabagina protected over 1,000 refugees in one of these establishments.",
        "answer": [
          "hotels",
          "Hotel des Mille Collines",
          "Hotel Rwanda"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man refused a promotion to a desk job by saying “every poor fellow in the trenches must do his duty.” Donald Cunnel is credited with inflicting a serious head wound on this man, who attempted to kill Wilfred May but was stopped by Arthur Brown. Propaganda about this man stated the British would automatically award a Victoria Cross to anyone that could kill him. The Flying Circus was led by, for ten points, what World War I German aviator commonly known by a colorful noble title?",
        "answer": [
          "Manfred Albrecht Freiherr von Richthofen",
          "the Red Baron"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the deaths of Richthofen and Wilhelm Reinhard, command of The Flying Circus was given to this man. During World War II, this Nazi was named Reichsmarschall and commanded the Luftwaffe.",
        "answer": "Hermann Wilhelm Goering"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location is home to the Timbisha Shoshone tribe, who use this location’s clay to make a red ochre [“oak-er”] paint. Accumulated salts in this location’s Badwater Basin have made its water undrinkable. In July 1913, this location’s Furnace Creek reached 134 degrees Fahrenheit, the hottest temperature ever recorded in the Western hemisphere. For ten points, name this location in the Mojave Desert of California, the lowest point in the US.",
        "answer": "Death Valley National Park"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Death Valley was proclaimed a National Park by this President, one month before he left office. This man’s Presidential library is in West Branch, Iowa, and his home in California is now the official residence of the President of Stanford University.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle was preceded by a gift of sports balls to remind the winning king that he should stick to tennis. The fall of Harfleur prompted the losing side to fight this battle. At this battle, the order to kill all prisoners was given after Henry V feared that his baggage train would be overrun. This battle’s losing side could not use cavalry thanks to stakes placed in muddy ground; instead the winning side’s longbowmen fired at will. For ten points, name this 1415 battle fought on St. Crispin’s Day, a victory for England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The English longbow also played a big role in this 1346 battle, where it prevailed over Genoese crossbows. Shortly after this battle, Calais [cah-lay] fell to England.",
        "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This policy was largely ignored by Congress as senators flocked to buy from “the man in the green-hat,” George Cassiday. Neal Dow became one of the first mayors to implement this policy under the Maine Law. Contraband violating this policy was destroyed by a hatchet-wielding Carrie Nation from the WCTU. This policy became law when the Volstead Act was enacted to carry out the Eighteenth Amendment. For ten points, name this 1920s policy that banned liquor throughout the US.",
        "answer": [
          "Prohibition",
          "temperance"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Prohibition, this leader of the Chicago Outfit, known as Scarface, made massive profits smuggling alcohol.",
        "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Capone"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In an unfinished story from this collection, Canace finds a falcon who was abandoned by her lover and then shows a romantic interest in her brother, who is also Genghis Khan’s son. In this collection’s first story, Palamon and Arcite fight in a massive battle to win Emily’s hand in marraige. Characters in this work include the Squire and his father, the Knight, who tell stories during their pilgrimage to the shrine of Thomas Becket. For ten points, name this story collection by Geoffrey Chaucer.",
        "answer": "The Canterbury Tales"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Geoffrey Chaucer wrote The Canterbury Tales in this language, which was in use from approximately the Norman conquest of Britain through the 16th century.",
        "answer": "Middle English"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s Operation Griffin included a violation of the Hague Convention when Otto Skorzeny dressed his troops in enemy uniforms. During this battle, American troops were fired on after surrendering at Malmedy. Anthony McAuliffe led a spirited defense of the town of Bastogne in this battle, whose losing side tried to use tanks to recreate the 1941 invasion of France. For ten points, name this 1944 battle that made a namesake shape in Allied lines.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Bulge",
          "Operation Watch on the Rhine",
          "Wacht am Rhein",
          "Ardennes Counteroffensive before “Ardennes” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The siege of Bastogne was lifted by this American commander of the Third Army. He was briefly disgraced for slapping a shell-shocked soldier during the Sicily landings.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A type of this disease that makes surgery difficult was discovered by Henry Pancoast. Fritz Lickint experimented with X-raying the spleen as a cure for this disease and coined the term for a “passive” cause of it. Scientists in Nazi Germany discovered the link between this disease and asbestos. In the late 1990s, Philip Morris admitted that its products cause this disease. For ten points, name this type of cancer often caused by smoking tobacco.",
        "answer": "lung cancer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term for smoke inhaled by non-smokers developed out of Fritz Lickint’s theories about the dangers of “passive smoking.” Governments have cited the dangers of this type of environmental exposure to smoke when passing laws banning smoking in public.",
        "answer": [
          "second-hand smoke",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First country the US declared war on, doing so in 1812.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Military title assigned to the President in the Constitution as head of the armed forces.",
          "answer": "Commander-in-Chief do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Article of the Constitution that details the President’s powers and roles, including that title.",
          "answer": "Article 2 of the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cuban naval base used by the US to detain terror suspects and enemy combatants.",
          "answer": [
            "Guantanamo Bay Naval Base",
            "Gitmo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 1973 law that restricts the President’s power to deploy armed troops beyond 60 days.",
          "answer": "War Powers Act or Resolution, Law, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Writ that prevents unlawful detention but was suspended unlawfully by Abraham Lincoln during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "writ of habeas corpus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Yugoslavian country, unrecognized by Serbia, whose 1999 bombing led Tom Campbell to sue Bill Clinton.",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        },
        {
          "question": "1952 Supreme Court case that limited President Truman’s ability to seize private property during war.",
          "answer": [
            "Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company vs. Sawyer",
            "Youngstown Steel case",
            "Steel Seizure case"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Soviet Union",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Successor state to the Soviet Union whose capital is Moscow.",
          "answer": "Russia or Russian Federation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who ordered the death of Leon Trotsky and was succeeded by Nikita Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country where the Soviets crushed Imre Nagy’s [nahj’s] rebellion in 1956.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "1959 event in which Nixon and Khrushchev debated capitalism and communism in a model home.",
          "answer": "Kitchen Debate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genocidal famine in Ukraine from 1932-33.",
          "answer": "Holodomor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for both US-Soviet treaties that limited ballistic missile production.",
          "answer": "SALT 1 and/or 2 or Strategic Arms Limitation Talks"
        },
        {
          "question": "1921 rebellion whose suppression led to the development of the New Economic Policy.",
          "answer": "Kronstadt Rebellion"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title given to the rulers of ancient Egypt.",
          "answer": "pharaoh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primary Egyptian river that flooded during the season of Akhet.",
          "answer": "Nile River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boy king whose tomb was re-discovered by Howard Carter in 1922.",
          "answer": "King Tutankhamun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stone dedicated to Ptolemy V that was used to decipher hieroglyphics.",
          "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
        },
        {
          "question": "1274 BC battle against the Hittites, the largest chariot battle in history.",
          "answer": "Battle of Kadesh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document that provides instructions for those being judged by Ma’at.",
          "answer": "Egyptian Book of the Dead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive rock temples of Ramesses the Great and Nefertari built in Nubia.",
          "answer": "Abu Simbel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler who briefly succeeded Akhenaten, but who may actually just have been Nefertiti disguised as a man.",
          "answer": "Smenkhare or Smenkhkare"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, the “Draft Muskie” movement emerged to break a deadlocked convention. John B. Anderson ran as an independent in this election. Controversy from the (20 pts)",
        "Chappaquiddick incident 11 years earlier damaged Ted Kennedy’s chances of being nominated during this year. Despite the “voodoo economics” attack in this year’s primaries, (10 pts)",
        "George H.W. Bush was nominated for Vice President. The failure to resolve the Iran Hostage Crisis helped doom a re-election campaign in, for ten points, what year in which Jimmy Carter lost 44 states to Ronald Reagan?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential Election of 1980"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This modern day country was briefly mortgaged in the 16th century to a German banking family whose sons wanted to search for the Fountain of Youth. This country’s city of Coro is one of the oldest European cities founded in the Americas. This country, which was named for (20 pts)",
        "stilted houses in lagoons that reminded Spanish colonists of a European city, is officially a “Bolivarian Republic” to commemorate (10 pts)",
        "Simon Bolivar, who was born here. For ten points, name this country where Spanish colonists founded cities like Maracaibo and Caracas."
      ],
      "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An early version of this work uses the phrase “waiting in the weeds,” later changed to “waiting in the wings.” In this work, a boy sings in French, then recites a poem on his ninth (20 pts)",
        "birthday to his father. The protagonist of this work is told to “talk less” and “smile more” by the antagonist, who later laments that “the world was (10 pts)",
        "wide enough” for both himself and the title character after they duel at Weehawken. For ten points, name this Lin-Manuel Miranda musical about the first treasury secretary, who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hamilton: An American Musical",
        "“Alexander Hamilton” before “French” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group formed the Confederation of Cologne and conducted a bombardment of Copenhagen, forcing Valdemar IV to grant them increased privileges. This group was plagued by the forces of Albert of Mecklenburg and the (20 pts)",
        "Victual Brothers, and it suffered a setback when Ivan III shut down their operations in Novgorod. This group was prominent in Bergen and Stralsund, but it was dominated by (10 pts)",
        "Lu¨beck in its early stages. A series of kontor trading posts was administered by, for ten points, what Northern European merchants guild formed during the Late Middle Ages?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hanseatic League",
        "Hansa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Domitian added the purple faction and a faction named for this material to chariot races. A palace on the future site of the Colosseum built by Nero was known as the house of this material. When Heinrich (20 pts)",
        "Schliemann discovered an artifact of this material in Mycenae, it convinced him he found the body of a legendary Homeric king. This material, which is combined with (10 pts)",
        "ivory to make chryselephantine sculptures, was used to mint a coin worth 25 denarii [day-NAR-ee-ee] called the aureus. The funeral mask of Agamemnon is made of, for ten points, what yellowish precious metal?"
      ],
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Van Orden sued this state in 2002 to take down a display of the Ten Commandments; the case was argued at the Supreme Court by this state’s Attorney General, who became Governor after defeating pro-choice State Senator Wendy (20 pts)",
        "Davis in 2014. The previous governor of this state currently serves as head of the Department of Energy, a department that he proposed to eliminate in his 2012 presidential bid. Another former governor of this state promoted the (10 pts)",
        "No Child Left Behind Act after he was elected president in 2000. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by Greg Abbott, Rick Perry, and George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hostilities that this treaty failed to end were later resolved through the Treaties of Baden and Rastatt. Under this treaty, 200 years after Tordesillas, Portugal’s control of Brazil was finally recognized. Great Britain gained (20 pts)",
        "Gibraltar and the asiento, a monopoly on the slave trade, through this treaty. Under this treaty, a claim to the (10 pts)",
        "French throne was renounced by Philip of Anjou so that he could be king of an Iberian country. For ten points, name this treaty that ended the War of Spanish Succession."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty or Peace, etc. of Utrecht"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man claimed New England was not guilty of an intent to dissolve the Union in a speech against James Monroe’s conscription plan. Following John Tyler’s decision to break with party lines, this man was the only member of Tyler’s (20 pts)",
        "cabinet not to resign. In a reply to Robert Hayne, this man declared that the US government was “made (10 pts)",
        "for the people, made by the people, and answerable to the people.” For ten points, name this Massachusetts senator who said “Liberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable!”"
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel Webster"
    }
  ]
}